PHYSICAL: WELCOME TO MONGOLIA
물리적: 몽골에 오신 것을 환영합니다
-I'm alive! -Wow.
-나는 살아있다! -우와.
I'm alive.
나는 살아있다.
Hey, Amotti.
안녕, 아모티.
This is for skincare.
스킨케어용이에요.
Try it on your skin.
피부에 사용해 보세요.
There's horse poop in it.
말똥이 들어있어요.
Horse poop?
말똥?
How do people even get here?
사람들은 어떻게 여기까지 올 수 있나요?
Can cars actually get here?
실제로 자동차가 여기에 들어올 수 있나요?
This place is amazing. I can't believe I'm here.
이곳은 정말 놀랍습니다. 내가 여기 있다는 게 믿기지 않는다.
-I'm on a Mongolian plain. -Seriously.
-저는 몽골 평원에 있어요. -진지하게.
It really is a Mongolian plain.
그야말로 몽골 평원이다.
Let's check it out.
확인해 봅시다.
Wow, this is so cool.
와, 정말 멋지네요.
They have all sorts of animals.
그들은 온갖 종류의 동물을 가지고 있습니다.
When you look at them this way,
그들을 이렇게 보면,
they seem to belong to another era.
그들은 다른 시대에 속한 것 같습니다.
-I know. -Seriously.
-알아요. -진지하게.
Their animals and clothing are from back in the day.
그들의 동물과 의복 옛날부터 왔습니다.
Is that what they wear every day?
그게 그 사람들이 매일 입는 옷인가요?
I think they do here.
제 생각엔 여기서 그런 것 같아요.
It looks like traditional attire.
전통복장 같네요.
That horse is cool.
그 말은 멋지다.
It's waving its front leg.
앞다리를 흔들고 있습니다.
Hey!
여기요!
Hey, our feet sink right in!
이봐, 우리 발이 딱 빠졌어!
Look at our shoes.
우리 신발 좀 보세요.
No, please!
아니, 제발!
Hey, what the heck?
이봐, 도대체 뭐야?
Hold on!
기다리다!
-My feet are wet now. -Come on.
- 지금 발이 젖었어요. -어서 해봐요.
-I'm serious. -Give me a break.
-진심이에요. -나 좀 쉬게 해주세요.
I'm in trouble.
나는 곤경에 빠졌다.
Dong-hyun, mine only come up to here.
동현아, 난 여기까지만 와.
Wow, look at the dogs.
와, 개들 좀 보세요.
They're so cool.
그들은 정말 멋지다.
Sain baina uu.
사인바이나우.
-Sain baina uu. -Hello.
-세인 바이나 우. -안녕하세요.
-Hello!
-안녕하세요!
Is he the chief?
그 사람이 대장인가요?
Welcome to Mongolia!
몽골에 오신 것을 환영합니다!
LKHAGVA-OCHIR TEAM MONGOLIA
LKHAGVA-OCHIR 팀 몽골
It's Ochir!
오치르입니다!
-But tomorrow-- -Look!
-하지만 내일은-- -보세요!
Let's go!
갑시다!
EDDIE WILLIAMS TEAM AUSTRALIA
에디 윌리엄스 호주 팀
Eddie, what are you doing here?
에디, 여기서 뭐 하는 거야?
I didn't recognize you.
나는 당신을 인식하지 못했습니다.
I didn't recognize Eddie at all!
나는 에디를 전혀 알아보지 못했습니다!
LET ME IN THE GROUP HUG
그룹 포옹에 참여하게 해주세요
TOGETHER
함께
He looks totally Mongolian.
완전 몽골인처럼 생겼네요.
Mongold tavtai moril.
몽골드 타브타이 모릴.
I didn't expect to see them here.
여기서 그들을 볼 줄은 몰랐습니다.
Meeting up like this feels like
이런 만남은 이런 느낌이야
something from centuries ago,
몇 세기 전에 있었던 일인데,
given the surroundings and the horses.
주변 환경과 말을 고려하면.
Hold on!
기다리다!
I'm scared.
나는 무서워요.
I'm riding already?
나 벌써 타고 있는 거야?
Amotti! Take your horse and go!
아모티! 말을 타고 가세요!
-Dong-hyun, you're riding? -Yeah.
-동현아, 타고 있어? -응.
This feels really stable.
정말 안정적인 느낌이에요.
What are you riding?
당신은 무엇을 타고 있습니까?
-A camel? -No, it's a yak.
- 낙타요? -아니야, 야크야.
Oh, a yak?
아, 야크요?
Wow, he looks cool.
와, 그 사람 멋있어 보이는데.
Go!
가다!
Do I hold onto this?
나는 이것을 붙잡고 있는가?
What do I hold?
나는 무엇을 들고 있나요?
This right here?
바로 여기요?
-Change to a camel. -Yes, please.
- 낙타로 갈아탄다. -네, 부탁드립니다.
Do I grab the hump--
혹을 잡나요--
Wow, I've never been on a camel before.
와, 저는 낙타를 타본 적이 없어요.
This hump though…
그래도 이 고비는…
It's not meant to be a handle, right?
손잡이로 쓰려고 만든 건 아니죠?
This hump is so weird.
이 고비가 참 이상해요.
It's so weird and hard.
참 이상하고 어렵습니다.
-It's really comfortable. -Yeah.
-정말 편해요. -응.
The humps make it perfect to sit.
혹이 있어서 앉기에 완벽합니다.
-It feels like riding a sedan. -Yeah.
- 세단을 타는 느낌이에요. -응.
It really feels like a handle, though.
그래도 정말 손잡이 같은 느낌이에요.
It makes it easy to sit.
앉기 편해집니다.
FROM DONG-HYUN'S PHONE
동현의 전화에서
This is great.
이것은 훌륭합니다.
I woke up
나는 일어났다
and suddenly found myself here.
그리고 갑자기 여기 있는 걸 발견했어요.
I never could've imagined this.
나는 이것을 상상도 할 수 없었습니다.
Do they live here?
그들은 여기에 살고 있나요?
Head.
머리.
Right hand. Left hand.
오른손. 왼손.
Right leg. Left leg.
오른쪽 다리. 왼쪽 다리.
Butt.
대상.
Let's go.
갑시다.
PHYSICAL: WELCOME TO MONGOLIA
물리적: 몽골에 오신 것을 환영합니다
This is my first time.
이번이 처음입니다.
It's a real ger.
진짜 게르입니다.
-Hey, there's food. -Awesome.
-야, 음식이 있어. -엄청난.
It's warm.
따뜻해요.
-Wow. -It's so warm.
-우와. -너무 따뜻해요.
It smells like the cheese we had yesterday.
치즈 냄새가 나네요 우리는 어제 있었다.
The heating is amazing in here.
여기 난방이 정말 훌륭해요.
There are sitting rules here.
여기에는 앉는 규칙이 있습니다.
Certain people sit in the middle, on the right,
가운데에 앉으시는 분들도 계시고, 오른쪽에,
on the left, and so on.
왼쪽에 등등.
-You're going to go here. -I'm an elder.
-여기로 가세요. -저는 연장자입니다.
Right, the elder sits first.
그렇죠, 장로님이 먼저 앉으세요.
Oh, we sit in order.
아, 우리는 순서대로 앉아 있어요.
Younger people here.
여기 젊은 사람들이요.
Oh, you're the host.
아, 호스트이시군요.
The host sits all the way inside.
호스트는 안쪽에 앉습니다.
Some sit here too.
일부는 여기에도 앉습니다.
I think the father and mother, right?
제 생각에는 아버지와 어머니인 것 같아요. 그렇죠?
What's that?
그게 뭐야?
How do I do it? Like this?
어떻게 해야 하나요? 이와 같이?
I don't smell anything.
냄새도 안 나고
Try it. I don't smell it.
시도해 보세요. 냄새가 나지 않아요.
Hey, there's powder.
아, 가루가 있어요.
Powder?
가루?
Won't you sneeze?
재채기 안 할 거야?
IMMEDIATELY GREETS HIM, MONGOLIAN-STYLE
즉시 그에게 인사합니다. 몽골 스타일
How are you? Have you been well this winter?
잘 지내세요? 이번 겨울 잘 보내셨나요?
Yes, I have.
예, 그렇습니다.
Oh, and then you exchange.
아, 그러면 교환하세요.
You exchange with each other.
당신은 서로 교환합니다.
This smells different.
이건 냄새가 달라요.
I think they exchange their own distinct scents.
교환하는 것 같아요 그들만의 독특한 향기.
Right?
오른쪽?
-Very simple. -Is it deep-fried?
-아주 간단해요. -튀김인가요?
Hey! These two taste great together!
여기요! 둘이 같이 먹어도 맛있어요!
It's like really fresh butter.
정말 신선한 버터 같아요.
Like whipped cream mixed with butter.
마치 버터에 휘핑크림을 섞은 것처럼요.
Like this.
이와 같이.
Holy cow!
이런 소!
It's so good.
너무 좋아요.
YET ANOTHER GIFT PRESENTATION
또 다른 선물 증정
This is the traditional costume we wear for Naadam in the summer.
이것이 우리가 입는 전통의상이다 여름에는 나담을 위해.
Like this?
이와 같이?
Are they the same people from yesterday?
어제와 같은 사람들인가요?
It's a group performance.
단체공연이에요
It seems they'll use those stones too.
그 사람들도 그 돌을 사용할 것 같군요.
Holy cow.
이런 소.
It sounds so grand.
정말 웅장하게 들리네요.
Wow, I couldn't tell their voices apart.
와, 그들의 목소리를 구분할 수 없었습니다.
That was so cool.
정말 멋졌어요.
Maybe it's because we're inside, but it sounded majestic.
아마도 우리가 안에 있기 때문일 거예요. 하지만 그 소리는 장엄하게 들렸습니다.
PHYSICAL: WELCOME TO MONGOLIA
물리적: 몽골에 오신 것을 환영합니다
Wow, it's sunny.
와, 날씨가 맑네요.
So many horses!
말이 너무 많아요!
Listen to the hoofbeats.
발굽소리를 들어보세요.
That's the sound of war coming.
전쟁이 다가오는 소리입니다.
You hear hoofbeats pounding when there's a war.
발굽소리가 쿵쿵거리는 소리가 들린다 전쟁이 나면.
-They're beautiful. -These horses have great stamina.
- 정말 아름다워요. - 이 말은 체력이 아주 좋습니다.
They're built for long distances
장거리용으로 제작되었습니다.
and don't eat a lot.
그리고 많이 먹지 마세요.
Mongolian horses are the best warhorses.
몽골 말은 최고의 군마입니다.
What is it? What's going on?
그것은 무엇입니까? 무슨 일이야?
Seriously?
진지하게?
For real?
진짜요?
Are you serious?
진심인가요?
FAILED
실패함
-Can he really catch it? -He's really doing this?
- 정말 잡을 수 있을까? - 정말 저 사람이 이러는 걸까요?
Don't be scared! You got this!
겁먹지 마세요! 당신은 이것을 얻었습니다!
Show us how it's done!
어떻게 완료되었는지 보여주세요!
FAILED
실패함
Let me try.
시도해 보겠습니다.
Doing it that way will tangle the rope.
그렇게 하면 밧줄이 엉키게 됩니다.
They're running away!
그들은 도망가고 있어요!
It looks like your first time.
처음 뵙는 것 같습니다.
It's because he's from the city.
그 사람이 도시 출신이거든요.
-Can Ochir do it? -I think he can pull it off.
- 오키르가 할 수 있을까? - 내 생각엔 그 사람이 해낼 수 있을 것 같아.
Did he catch one?
그 사람이 하나 잡았나요?
Wait a minute.
잠깐 기다려요.
He's getting dragged away!
그는 끌려가고 있어요!
These horses are so strong.
이 말들은 정말 강해요.
Ochir.
오키르.
HORSE SKIING
승마
Horses are so strong.
말은 너무 강해요.
It was amazing.
정말 놀라웠어요.
He's really strong.
그는 정말 강해요.
This one looks a bit weak.
이건 좀 약해보이네요.
The white horse.
백마.
A DOCILE HORSE
유순한 말
-Elder. -It's the elder's horse!
- 장로. -어르신의 말입니다!
-Hey, elder! -This is an elder's horse.
-안녕하세요, 선배님! - 장로님의 말입니다.
Hold on a second.
잠깐만요.
Hey, Orkhon.
안녕, 오르콘.
TAKES AMOTTI'S REINS
아모티의 고삐를 잡다
No, Orkhon!
안돼, 오르콘!
What do I do?
어떻게 해야 하나요?
Orkhon, you can't leave me here.
오르혼, 당신은 나를 여기에 남겨둘 수 없어요.
This is nice.
이것은 좋은 것입니다.
EVERYONE HEADS OUT
모두가 밖으로 나간다
Wow, the camels are so cool.
와, 낙타들 정말 멋지네요.
Gosh.
이런.
Let's go around that way.
그쪽으로 돌아갑시다.
Where? Over there?
어디? 저기요?
Make a wider turn! Keep going!
더 넓게 회전하세요! 계속하세요!
Let's go farther out.
더 멀리 나가자.
THE CAMELS FOLLOW BEHIND
낙타들이 뒤를 따라온다
This is so much fun.
정말 재미있어요.
So this is how the nomads get around.
그래서 이것이 유목민들이 돌아다니는 방법입니다.
The yak and camels pull their belongings.
야크와 낙타는 소지품을 끌어당깁니다.
This is incredible.
정말 놀랍습니다.
No, no!
아니, 아니!
Hey, the pace is picking up.
안녕하세요, 속도가 빨라지고 있습니다.
A little bit faster, okay?
조금 더 빨리, 알았지?
Hey, my horse is going faster.
야, 내 말이 더 빨리 가고 있구나.
Go, go.
가, 가.
We're picking up speed.
속도가 빨라지고 있습니다.
We're going fast!
우리는 빨리 가고 있어요!
Jeez, I'm so scared.
이런, 너무 무서워요.
We're galloping.
우리는 질주하고 있습니다.
They're getting ready to gallop.
그들은 질주할 준비를 하고 있습니다.
-Orkhon? -Yes?
-오르콘? -예?
Holy cow, that's so cool!
이런 소, 정말 멋지네요!
That's amazing!
정말 놀랍습니다!
Riding is a basic skill for everyone here.
승마는 여기 계신 모든 분들의 기본 기술입니다.
He's riding with no hands!
그는 손 없이 타고 있어요!
Not bad, Orkhon.
나쁘지 않네, 오르콘.
Look at them coming. It's so cool.
그들이 오는 것을 보세요. 정말 멋지다.
THE EXCITED PAIR
흥분된 쌍
That was really cool.
정말 멋졌어요.
Riding isn't scary anymore. It's fun.
라이딩은 더 이상 무섭지 않습니다. 재미있다.
It's really fun.
정말 재미있어요.
Hey, there.
안녕, 거기.
Let's get off now and do some archery.
이제 내려서 양궁을 해보자.
Warriors, mount up!
전사들이여, 올라타라!
QUICK EQUIPMENT CHECK
빠른 장비 점검
Hey, there.
안녕, 거기.
Oh, no.
안 돼.
I know I shouldn't laugh, but…
웃으면 안 된다는 건 알지만…
PHYSICAL: WELCOME TO MONGOLIA
물리적: 몽골에 오신 것을 환영합니다
We're going to try archery now.
이제 양궁을 시도해 보겠습니다.
Right here?
바로 여기요?
So we hit the target from here?
그럼 여기서 목표물을 맞추는 건가요?
You shoot from here.
여기에서 촬영하세요.
Competition?
경쟁?
1ST MINI QUEST: AIM FOR THE TARGET
첫 번째 미니 퀘스트: 목표를 목표로 하세요
The players I feel most pressured by
가장 부담감을 느끼는 선수는
are the Mongolians because they have
몽골인인 이유는 그들이
this celebration gesture.
이 축하 몸짓.
Seeing this makes me think they'll be good at archery.
이걸 보니 생각이 나네요 그 사람들은 양궁을 잘할 거예요.
I'm really confident.
나는 정말로 자신감을 갖고 있다.
ARCHERY DEMONSTRATION
양궁 시범
He moved his index finger down.
그는 집게손가락을 아래로 움직였다.
Draw back as much as possible.
가능한 한 많이 뒤로 물러납니다.
GOT CLOSE ON HIS FIRST SHOT
첫 번째 샷에 가까워졌습니다.
ORKHON TAKES HIS STANCE
오르콘이 자신의 입장을 취하다
Go ahead and try, city boy.
어서 시도해 보세요, 도시 소년님.
PLAYER 1: KIM DONG-HYUN
플레이어 1: 김동현
I'm a southpaw, so…
저는 사우스포라서...
-A southpaw? -Yeah.
-왼손잡이요? -응.
You need to be really strong.
당신은 정말 강해야합니다.
It's an individual match,
개인전인데,
but since Mongolia, Australia, and Korea went up against each other before,
하지만 몽골, 호주, 한국 이후 예전에는 서로 싸웠는데,
I'll do it with that mindset.
그런 마음으로 해보겠습니다.
KNOCKS DOWN TWO ON THE SIDE
측면에서 두 명을 쓰러 뜨립니다.
-Hey, it worked. -You got two.
-이봐요, 성공했어요. - 두 개 있어요.
I think I can do it.
나는 그것을 할 수 있다고 생각합니다.
The moment I saw the bow, I felt as if I'd shot with it long ago.
활을 본 순간, 마치 오래 전에 그걸로 촬영한 것 같은 느낌이 들었습니다.
If past lives exist,
전생이 존재한다면,
I think I remember shooting from the top of a castle.
기억나는 것 같아요 성 꼭대기에서 촬영.
Orkhon, you seem nervous.
오르콘, 너 긴장한 것 같구나.
SECOND ARROW
두 번째 화살표
HITS ONE
히트 원
It keeps going to the left.
계속 왼쪽으로 갑니다.
One more left.
하나 더 남았습니다.
Why?
왜?
He has one more arrow left.
그에게는 화살이 하나 더 남았습니다.
Don't forget the rules.
규칙을 잊지 마세요.
City boy is competitive.
도시 소년은 경쟁적이다.
THIRD ARROW
세 번째 화살표
Invalid.
유효하지 않습니다.
-The ground. -It hit the ground.
-땅. -땅에 떨어졌어요.
It's invalid.
유효하지 않습니다.
It'd still hurt if you got hit with it!
맞으면 아직도 아플 것 같아요!
It'd still hurt if it bounced off and hit you!
그래도 아플 텐데 그것이 튕겨져 당신을 때렸다면!
But it hit the ground first.
하지만 먼저 땅에 떨어졌습니다.
There's no rule that says that!
그렇게 말하는 규칙은 없습니다!
THE LAST SHOT WAS INVALID
마지막 샷이 유효하지 않았습니다
KIM DONG-HYUN: 3
김동현: 3
You have to draw back really hard.
정말 열심히 뒤로 물러나야 합니다.
South Korea is famous for gukgung, traditional Korean archery.
한국은 국궁으로 유명하고, 한국의 전통 활쏘기.
I'll show them what Korean genes are made of.
내가 보여줄게 한국의 유전자는 무엇으로 만들어졌는가.
This is his thing.
이것은 그의 것입니다.
For some reason, he doesn't lose at games like this.
어떤 이유로, 그는 이런 게임에서는 지지 않습니다.
Jeez, this really hurts.
이런, 정말 아프다.
Hey, I told you it wasn't easy!
아, 쉽지 않다고 말했잖아!
I do live in an apartment.
저는 아파트에 살고 있어요.
Hey, I can't pull this.
이봐, 난 이걸 당길 수가 없어.
I told you it wasn't easy, Amotti.
쉽지 않다고 말했잖아, 아모티.
My hands are frozen!
내 손이 얼었다!
My hands…
내 손이…
He drew back, but it fell right in front of him.
그는 뒤로 물러났다, 그런데 그 사람 바로 앞에 떨어졌어요.
It was really funny and cute.
정말 웃기고 귀여웠어요.
His muscles are for show.
그의 근육은 보여주기 위한 것입니다.
That really hurt.
정말 아팠어요.
-Draw back really hard. -I can't. My hands are frozen.
-정말 열심히 뒤로 물러납니다. - 할 수 없어요. 내 손이 얼었다.
NO UNSOLICITED ADVICE
원치 않는 조언 금지
You have to pull really hard.
정말 열심히 당겨야 합니다.
That was all recoil.
그것은 모두 반동이었습니다.
I got it now. I'm going for an arc, then.
나는 지금 그것을 얻었다. 그럼 호를 그리러 가겠습니다.
You got this!
당신은 이것을 얻었습니다!
Pull back hard.
세게 뒤로 당기세요.
Gosh, it's so cold.
맙소사, 너무 추워요.
Aren't his hands cold?
손이 차갑지 않나요?
Wow, he'll hit all the pink targets.
와, 그 분은 분홍색 목표물을 모두 맞추실 거예요.
Warriors!
전사들이여!
Mount up!
탑승하세요!
Hey, I'm in first place.
이봐요, 제가 1등이에요.
This is harder than expected.
이것은 예상보다 어렵습니다.
Eddie, what was that?
에디, 그게 뭐였지?
He looks so cool.
그는 정말 멋져 보인다.
I think he'll do well.
내 생각엔 그 사람이 잘할 것 같아.
Look at his stance.
그의 입장을보세요.
What the heck?
도대체 뭐야?
TAKES CAREFUL AIM
신중하게 조준합니다
Look at that draw.
저 추첨을 보세요.
No more adjusting.
더 이상 조정할 필요가 없습니다.
KNOCKS DOWN THREE
3개를 쓰러뜨리다
Didn't it bounce off?
튕겨나온거 아냐?
Good aim.
좋은 목표입니다.
OCHIR: 3 (NOT 2 POINTS)
OCHIR: 3 (2점 아님)
LAST PLAYER: CITY BOY
마지막 플레이어: 시티보이
Let's go, city boy.
가자, 도시 소년.
Right, city boy.
그렇지, 도시 소년.
Looking good.
좋아 보인다.
He's going to break it.
그는 그것을 깨뜨릴 것입니다.
Gosh, he's strong.
맙소사, 그는 강해요.
Wow.
우와.
VERY STRONG, BUT NOTHING ELSE
매우 강력하지만 다른 것은 없습니다
You're getting closer to the punishment.
당신은 처벌에 점점 가까워지고 있습니다.
Don't pull back too hard.
너무 세게 뒤로 당기지 마십시오.
The way I see it,
제가 보기엔,
Orkhon isn't very good
오르콘은 별로 안 좋아
because he lacks experience.
경험이 부족하기 때문이다.
One of the Mongolians will win first place.
몽골인 중 한 명 1위를 차지하게 됩니다.
It's Mong Ji-hun.
몽지훈입니다.
It's my circus family.
우리 서커스 가족이에요.
He's incredible!
그는 정말 대단해요!
It's khorkhog!
코르코그예요!
This is so good!
정말 좋아요!
I hope you'll be good students.
좋은 학생이 되길 바랍니다.
That hurts!
아파요!
I don't think I've ever seen him this excited.
내 생각엔 아닌 것 같아 나는 그가 이렇게 흥분하는 것을 본 적이 있다.
Subtitle translation by: Jenny Kim
자막번역: 김제니